Guide to the New York State Legislature Portrait Prints Collection 1798 PR 213
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
New York State Legislature Portrait Prints Collection
1798
PR 213
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
1.58 Linear feet (1 box)
Collection consists of 19 stipple engraved plates containing medallion profile portraits of 57 prominent men who served in the New York State Legislature in 1798.
Provenance
Collection comprised of multiple gifts and acquisitions: 7 of the 8 plates in series I were given to the N-YHS in 1807 by John Pintard, who had previously been presented with the set by Rev. Uzal Ogden. The eighth plate was received by the Society as a gift from Mr. Harry Shaw Newman. The plates in series II were a gift of Robert Goelet in April of 1978. Plates in series III were transferred from the Duane-Featherstonhaugh family papers.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to thirty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. See guidelines in Print Room for details.
Scope and Content Note
The New York State Legislature Portrait Prints collection holds stipple engraved plates of prominent men who served in elected positions in state government in 1798. The plates came from a variety of sources, and have been arranged in four series to reflect provenance. The history of the engravings is told by R.W.G. Vail in his article "The First New York State Mug Book: Portraits of the Legislature of 1798" (in "The New-York Historical Society Quarterly," vol. 35, no. 1, January 1951).
The engravings are attributed by Vail to the firm of Albany silversmith and engraver Isaac Hutton. Lithographic reproductions of some of the New York State Legislature portrait prints may be found in the Portrait File (PR-052).
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in four series based on provenance.
Jay, John, -- 1745-1829 -- Portraits; New York (State). -- Legislature -- (21st: 1798) -- Portraits; Ten Broeck, Dirck -- Portraits; Van Rensselaer, Stephen, -- 1764-1839 -- Portraits; New York (State) -- Officials and employees -- Portraits; Portraits; Prints; Statesmen in art; Stipple engravings
- Series I: New-York Historical Society Plates
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I holds what is apparently the only complete set of the portraits in existence. According to Vail, seven of the eight prints were given to the Society in 1807 by John Pintard, after he had received them from Reverend Uzal Ogden. The missing eighth plate was later acquired from Harry Shaw Newman. A second full set of plates was formerly held in the New York State Library in Albany, but was destroyed in the great library fire of 1911.
  - Governor John Jay and Lt. Governor Stephen Van Rensselaer, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Speaker of the House Dirck Ten Broeck, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Senators: L'Hommedieu, Gold, Jones, Cantine, Silvester, Graham, Thompson, Sanger, and Phelps, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Senators: Morris, White, VanVechten, Gansevoort, and Gelston; Assemblymen: Ogden, Warner, Howard, and Fonda, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Assemblymen: Hildreth, Mason, Henry, Bird, Jenkins, Denning, Hovey, Smith, and Foot, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Assemblymen: Morse, McNiel, Heermance, Clift, Fort, Hoag, Hall, Hogeboom, and Thomas, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Assemblymen: Williamson, Dewey, Bowen, Wood, Holly, Griswold, McFarland, De la Montagnie, and Prince, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Assemblymen: Holt, Bowman, Verplank, Schuyler, Van Alstyne, Clinton, Hogeboom, Benton, and Brown, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series II: Goelet Plates
  Series II holds five plates that were given to the Society in April 1978 by Robert Goelet. These prints have been trimmed to dimensions of printed border, 20.4 x 17.5 cm.
  - Senators: L'Hommedieu, Gold, Jones, Cantine, Silvester, Graham, Thompson, Sanger, and Phelps, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Senators: Morris, White, VanVechten, Gansevoort, and Gelston; Assemblymen: Ogden, Warner, Howard, and Fonda, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Assemblymen: Hildreth, Mason, Henry, Bird, Jenkins, Denning, Hovey, Smith, and Foot, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Assemblymen: Morse, McNiel, Heermance, Clift, Fort, Hoag, Hall, Hogeboom, and Thomas, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Assemblymen: Williamson, Dewey, Bowen, Wood, Holly, Griswold, McFarland, De la Montagnie, and Prince, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series III: Duane Plates
  Series III were, according to a note written on their former enclosure, "removed from Duane Papers VII." The four plates are damaged, each either cut or torn, and none are complete in having all nine portraits present.
  - Senators: Morris, White, VanVechten, Gansevoort, and Gelston; Assemblymen: Ogden, Warner, Howard, and Fonda, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Assemblymen: Morse, McNiel, Heermance, Clift, Fort, Hoag, Hall, Hogeboom, and Thomas, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Assemblymen: Williamson, Dewey, Bowen, Wood, Holly, Griswold, McFarland, De la Montagnie, and Prince, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Assemblymen: Holt, Bowman, Verplank, Schuyler, Van Alstyne, Clinton, Hogeboom, Benton, and Brown, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Series IV: Miscellaneous Plates
  Series IV holds two plates from an unknown source.
  - Senators: Morris, White, VanVechten, Gansevoort, and Gelston; Assemblymen: Ogden, Warner, Howard, and Fonda, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Assemblymen: Hildreth, Mason, Henry, Bird, Jenkins, Denning, Hovey, Smith, and Foot, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 15)